Cool. Hello everyone and welcome to CME
295 Transformers and large language
models.
So, my name is Afshin and I will be
teaching this class with Shirvin who's
in the back.
And before I start, I'm just going to
introduce ourselves.
And so, we're twin brothers and we
actually had kind of a similar career
backgrounds. So, we both went to a
school in France called Telecom Paris.
And then we each went our way. So, on my
end I went to MIT and then Shirvin went
to Stanford to do the ICME master's
program.
And after that, I guess our industry
background is very similar as well. So,
I first went to Uber
and then Shirvin came to Uber as well
and then Shirvin left to Google and I
went to Google
and then very recently I joined Netflix
and Shirvin joined Netflix as well and
we've been working on large language
models.
Um so yeah, I guess we have like
technical backgrounds and mostly
oriented towards LLMs.
Okay, so why are we doing this class?
Um so since 2020, Shirvin and I have
been specializing in NLP
and we've been giving this class in a
format of a workshop that was done in a
yearly basis. So, in 2021, 2022, 2023,
2024. You know, ChatGPT came in 2022 and
suddenly there was a lot of interest for
LLMs.
And so, it's actually last spring
that we started to offer this class as a
Stanford course
that is now called CME 295
and this is the second instance.
Cool.
So, what can you expect from this class?
So, first of all,
LLMs are basically
everywhere now and I guess our goal here
is two-fold.
So, the first one is
to learn about the underlying mechanism
that makes all this work and we're going
to see the transformer which is the
foundational architecture
that makes all this work. And then the
second thing is to know how these LLMs
are trained and where they are applied.
So, in case you're still wondering if
this class is good for you um I would
say that this class is great for people
who just in general have an interest in
this field
either because you wanted to make it
your career goal if you want to be a
research scientist or an ML scientist
or if you want to develop like a
personal project that relies on LLMs to
some extent. You just like knowing the
caveats, I guess what works, what
doesn't.
Or just say if you're in a separate
field and you just want to know how this
whole AI GenAI LLMs thing works and how
you can apply it to your domain.
Okay, so now in terms of prerequisites
I would say that
at a very minimum
you should have some foundations in ML
like basically know whether how a model
is trained what a neural network is and
also some basics in linear algebra. So,
basically how matrices are multiplied
for instance.
But even if you have kind of a
developing
I guess competency in this field, I
guess it's fine. We'll still be here to
help you out. I guess this is like the
ideal set of prerequisites.
Cool. So, still on the logistics.
So, this class will be held every Friday
from 3:30 to 5:20
and it will be held here.
So, this class is two units and you have
the choice to either take it as a letter
or a credit non-credit.
So, as you could tell from the from the
setup, we're basically recording this
class and if you cannot for some reason
attend this
you know this time this slots, we'll
make sure with Shirvin to make the
recordings available either tonight like
every Friday nights or on Saturday.
So, in terms of the grades
so what we're doing for this quarter is
to have two exams.
So, one is the midterm which will be
happening
during our fifth instance which is
October 24th.
And then the second exam will be the
final exam which will be held
like in the
on the you know in the week of the
December 8th. So, date is still TBD.
So, we'll let you know.
Cool.
So, every time we have a lecture we'll
be posting the slides and the recordings
on the website.
And in case you're interested, we also
have the syllabus in there so you can
know a little bit what are the topics
that we'll be talking about.
And
the class textbook is the super study
guide transformer LLMs. So, we have a
copy here in case you want to take a
look.
So yeah, I guess a lot of the concepts
that we have in this class will actually
be in the book. So, I guess it's a
helpful way to follow this as well.
And also we did
some kind of very short condensed
version of this whole class that we
called the VIP cheat sheet. So, this one
is available on GitHub in case you're
you're interested and yeah, we also
translated it into a number of languages
now.
By the way, if your language is not
there,
let us know and yeah, happy to work on
that as well together.
Okay, cool.
I think it's the last things on the
logistics part. So, in terms of
announcements, we'll be posting things
on Canvas. In case you have any
questions, you can of course reach out
to us. But there is also a tab on Canvas
that's called Ed.
I'm sure you're familiar.
So, yeah, just click on that, just post
your question and then Shirvin and I
will be responding.
And
yeah, I guess to reach out to us you
have this mailing list or just like you
know, we're just two so just ping us.
Cool. So
on the logistics, do we have any
questions so far? And one thing I forgot
to mention is that given that we're
recording this class
um
I guess if you're asking a question, it
may not be super clear for the viewer
what your question was. So, I'm going to
make an effort to just repeat your
question. It will sound weird but yeah,
I'll try to not forget.
But yeah. So, yeah, any questions so far
on the logistics?
Yep.
So, the question is whether there are
like coding parts in the exams. So, the
answer is no. So, the exams will purely
focus on concepts that we see in class.
And actually it's not meant to you know
trap you. So, I guess if you follow the
class, if you know you see the slides
and like the concepts that we see should
be fine.
Yep.
Oh yeah.
Question is if you're waitlisted, what
do you do?
I think so by experience, you know, a
lot of people will kind of finalize
their schedule. Some people will drop,
some won't. In case you're still
waitlisted, you know, come talk to us
but I'm pretty confident you know, it's
going to be okay because I think the
waitlist right now is like six.
So, yeah, things should be fine. Cool.
Yep.
They will be on the website and we'll
make sure to
um
also post it on Canvas.
Yep. So, the question was where are the
slides and they're on the website.
Cool. Yep.
So, question is on the weighting of the
exams. So, yeah, there is no homework.
So, 50% is midterm, 50% is final.
And no no grades, I mean no weights are
from that.
In particular, I mean if this class is
conflicting with something, just keep in
mind that we are recording this so I
mean it's fine if you if you cannot
attend the session. Yep.
That's right.
Oh, is the question that the final is
about just the second half of the class?
Um we've not we have not written the
exam yet but I think this is something
we're thinking of. So, yeah, the final
is probably going to be the second half,
about the second half of the topics.
Cool. Okay, long story short
50% midterm, 50% exam final exam
and yeah, it's a fun class.
Cool.
So, with that I'm going to just slowly
start the the class.
So, another thing that I wanted to
mention was every time we're talking
about something
you will see that at the bottom of the
slide there will be
source. It's mostly for So, first to
credit whatever we're quoting but also
for you to kind of dig into those
material a little more case you're
interested. Uh cuz of course we have
only like 2 hours per week and we're
going to have 9 or 10 weeks.
So there's nowhere near the, you know,
enough time for us to cover everything.
And the second disclaimer is you will
see that the field is full of
abbreviations.
So I myself was completely scared of
them when I started.
Uh but hopefully by the end of the class
you will have a mental mapping of what
these abbreviations mean with respect to
what they correspond to.
Um so yes, so if you have that mental
mapping towards the end of the class
then we'll know we did a good job.
So with that
um let's start.
And I guess we will start at the very
high level because I would just uh
assume that
um I guess we're starting from scratch.
Um
and we're going to talk about NLP in
general.
So NLP is going to be our first
abbreviation. So NLP stands for natural
language processing.
And it is a field that is around
like manipulating texts, just computing
things with text.
And at a very high level
can basically classify NLP tasks into
three buckets.
So the first bucket is what we call
classification.
So we have
an input text as an input.
And then what we want is to predict
something.
So one example is you have a movie
review
and you want to predict whether uh the
sentiment is positive, negative, or
neutral.
Uh so that's one example.
You can also have intent detection.
Uh just, you know, knowing what, for
instance, the person want to do. So
let's suppose you say
"I want to create an alarm for
tomorrow." So the intent here is create
an alarm.
So also to detect the language. So for
instance, if you write, I don't know, in
French, you want to detect that that
text is in French.
Topic modeling.
The second category is what we call
multi-classification.
So we still have a text as input.
But this time we predict more than one
thing.
So you have a number of tasks in that
bucket as well. So one that is very
called named entity recognition, aka
NER.
So what that task does is given an input
text, we want to basically label some
specific words. Like for instance,
identifying whether something is a
location or a time
and so on.
And then you have some other tasks as
well that are a little bit more on the
linguistic sides. I think they're less
trendy now, but I guess 10 years ago it
was something that people would study a
lot.
Uh so part of speech tagging, which is
about just figuring out which word is a,
you know, noun, a verb, etc.
Or some parsing related tasks or
dependency or constituency parsing.
And then the last bucket, which is very
popular these days, is the generation
bucket.
So you have an
a text as input. And you also have text
as output.
And here the length can be variable,
meaning you don't know what the length
of your output text will be
beforehand.
So here you have uh several tasks. So
for instance, you have machine
translation. So for instance, something
in English and I want it to, let's say,
uh German.
Question answering. So typically, you
know, the ChatGPT, Gemini that you're
using, you know, the assistant. So you
ask a question and you have a response.
And then you have like other
um
tasks as well like summarization. You
want to summarize an article, let's say.
Or just generate something.
So something can be generate codes,
generate a poem.
It can also be a lot of things.
Cool. So now what we do
is go through these tasks one by one
to just illustrate what people typically
handle with.
So we're going to start with the first
bucket, which is the classification
bucket.
And here we're going to illustrate this
with the sentiment extraction task.
So let's suppose we have a sentence,
"This teddy bear is so cute."
We want our model to predict, you know,
this to be a positive sentiment.
So typically what you would use is, you
know, data sets that are around the
sentiment extraction data sets. So I
mentioned movie reviews. So this is IMDb
critics, but you also have reviews about
products, Amazon reviews. Or you know,
tweets. Now I guess it's called X. So X
posts.
And the way you would evaluate such
outputs would be by typically using
traditional classification metrics.
Um so you have accuracy, which is, you
know, how many What what is the
percentage of the observations that you
correctly predicted?
But you also have two key metrics, which
I'm just going to uh remind. I'm not
sure if everyone knows about them. So
one is precision.
Which is out of all the positive
predictions that you made
which ones were correct?
And then the second one is recall.
Out of all the true labels
how many of them did you correctly
predict as being positive?
And uh you have uh this metric called
the F1 score, which basically takes the
harmonic mean of precision and recall.
To just give you one number.
So now you may wonder, you know, why do
you need all these metrics?
So the short answer is that sometimes
you have tasks and data sets where your
classes are very imbalanced.
So for instance, you can have, I don't
know, 99% of your data set that is
positive label and then only 1% of the
data set which is negative.
And so here if you take like a metric
like accuracy
it would be very misleading. Cuz if you
have uh model that would predict
everything as the majority class, then
you would have a, you know, great
classifier.
But it's not the case. So that's why
precision and recall really play a role.
So that's that's for the first one.
Okay. So now let's move to the second
category of NLP tasks. So this this one
is the multi-classification category.
So you have an input text and you
predict multiple things.
And uh we're illustrating this with the
NER task.
Which as I mentioned is about
identifying the category of given words.
And so here for instance, we want to
identify uh teddy bear as being an
entity.
Um I guess for that you would use
classification metrics, but not at the
sentence level, but more either at the
token level or at the entity type level.
And but by that I mean, let's suppose
you have a category
um let's say location
and you want to know how well you're
predicting words in that category. So
you would typically aggregate these
metrics
um as a function of that.
Cool.
Okay, let's go to the last category,
which is as I mentioned, the most
popular one. So this one is
text in
text out.
So I'm illustrating this with the
machine translation task. Which is
around
translating a text from a source
language to a target language. So here
you have the example with English to
French. So cute teddy bear is reading.
Uh noun some polish mignon lit.
Um so for that, I guess it's harder to
get data sets because here you you need
to have
pairs of text.
So you have a very popular data set
that's called WMT.
Which stands for workshop on machine
translation.
And that one contains a bunch of paired
sequences in different languages.
Uh so for instance, you have the English
French, English German coming from the
European Parliament's data set for
instance.
Um
Okay, so to evaluate those
to evaluate the performance of your
model
is actually a lot more tricky.
Because as you can imagine, you can have
many different ways to translate
something.
I'm sure many of us in the room uh are,
you know, bilingual, trilingual.
Um so yeah, that's that's what is making
it this hard.
So in the past, people have used several
rule-based metrics to do that.
So one that you may have heard is BLEU.
BLEU stands for bilingual evaluation
under study.
And
it is a measure of how well your
translation stands with respect to a
reference text.
Same story for ROUGE. Which is actually
a suite of metrics.
Um but kind of captures that in a
different way.
And you will see that machine learning
community is funny because BLEU, I'm not
sure if you know, in French means blue,
but rouge means red.
So I guess they tried to
kind of uh
uh add some some fun in this.
Um but the problem with these metrics is
that you always need a reference text.
So you basically need labels.
And in practice, having labels is very
cost expensive.
It takes a lot of time, a lot of money
to uh get these uh labels.
And we will see later in the class that
with uh the progress that we have made
in the LM space or that the community
has made in the LM space,
we can actually forego of these
reference-based metrics and go towards a
more reference-free
uh kind of metrics, and we will see that
later on.
And then the last metric that I will say
that people uh sometimes use is called
perplexity.
And perplexity only looks at the
probabilities that are output by the
model.
And it basically quantifies
how surprised
the model is by its outputs.
So blue and rouge, the higher the
better. Uh perplexity, the lower the
better.
And I guess um
LLMs have been uh kind of a hot topic
since 2022.
But actually the field goes way back,
way before that uh that year. So in the
'80s, uh we'll see it in a second, but
uh there's a class of models that were
actually kind of thought of
even in the '80s. And in the '90s, we
had uh LSTMs that we'll see also in a
second.
Um but the problem was during that time,
we didn't have the internet, we didn't
have a lot of computes.
And I guess this was one of the limiting
factors, which prevented these models
from like the
the models from today from being
trained.
And then more recently, uh we've had
several advances. So word-to-vec was
really one of the uh
kind of pioneering
um work in just um computing meaningful
embeddings.
And we'll see it in a second. And then
of course, we had the transformers,
which were uh part of a paper that was
published in 2017,
which is basically at the foundation of
of the models that you see today.
And then uh you know, these models, they
just uh were scaled up both by computes,
uh but also in in terms of like the data
that was used to train them. And you
know, that's how LLMs were dubbed. And I
guess these are more like the 2020s.
But yeah. I guess we'll see those.
Cool.
Any questions on
I guess the high level?
Everyone good?
Cool.
So
I guess
the first question that I want to ask
ourselves is
what we want to do is to have a model
that handles text.
But models, they understand numbers.
They don't really understand text.
So we need to somehow
do something with that text
to make it more
quantifiable, something that a model can
understand.
So if you look at a sentence, for
instance, "A cute teddy bear is
reading."
You first need to ask yourself,
how can you cut
this sentence
to pass it to a model?
So this part is called tokenization.
And what it entails is basically cutting
the text with respect to some
arbitrary unit of text.
So there are several ways of doing this.
I guess the first way is doing it
completely arbitrarily.
So here, for instance, you would have
"A" that would be one unit of text.
"Cute" would be another unit of text.
"Teddy bear" would be another one, and
so on.
And by the way, the unit of text is
called a token.
Which is why the method method is called
tokenization.
Another way would be to just separate by
words.
But I guess uh we would have, you know,
uh always pros and cons. Uh I guess um
one of the goals that we want to achieve
is for us to then be able to represent
these tokens in a meaningful way.
So
one con with doing this at the word
level is you will end up with words that
look similar,
but that are actually considered as
different tokens.
And I guess the limitation here is you
will need to compute embeddings for
these similar yet different tokens,
and somehow make their embeddings
similar.
So I'll give you an example.
So let's suppose I have the word "bear".
And then you have another word, plural
plural form "bears".
So these two words,
they are very similar. Just one is
singular, the other one is plural.
If we go ahead with the word level
tokenization,
then
we will end up with just two different
entities,
which are basically, yeah, just
considered as different.
Same with "run"
and then "runs", you know, variations of
verbs.
So for that reason,
people have uh kind of um
dug into
a category of token- tokenizers that are
called subword tokenizers,
which is around leveraging roots of
words in order to find what are the
common roots that we can find in this in
this words. So for instance, for "bear"
and "bears", you would have
the "bear" particle that would be uh
kind of shared.
And so I guess the pro is that you get
to leverage the root of the words.
But then the con here is that your
sequence
will be longer.
And we will see why this is a con
um I guess later on. I guess I can give
you um a preview.
Um so the complexity of these models
is also a function of the sequence
length.
So the more you have the more tokens you
have to process,
the more time it would take for your
models to model to run, because it needs
to basically process all these tokens.
So that's one con. So pro is it
leverages the root of words. Con is it
just
makes your
sequence longer.
Okay, you have a last category of
kind of ways of tokenizing things, which
is just going at the character level,
just like taking all characters.
So here,
I guess uh you and I, when we write, I
don't know, a message, we typically have
uh sometimes misspellings.
And with the subword uh way of
tokenizing things,
you may not uh be able to recognize a
word that has been misspelled.
And this is something that the character
level tokenizer can
uh
I guess take into consideration.
But here, the problem is you have a
sequence length that's much, much
longer, which will make your model uh I
guess take much more time to process uh
this sequence.
So that's one con.
And then uh the other con is I guess
when you want to represent each of these
tokens, I guess
it's very hard to know what a
representation of a letter really means.
Like, what does the representation of
the letter "u" mean?
Very hard.
Okay, cool. So I have just
a a quick recap. So word level is a
super naive way, super simple way of um
I guess dividing your text into
arbitrary units.
Um but then the problem is, as we
mentioned, we do not leverage the root
of words.
And uh I did not mention this, but
there's a term
whenever you cut something, and then um
at inference time, when you want to make
a prediction, I guess one
uh prerequisite that you have is that
you need to have the token
that you saw at training time, you need
to have it in your training set.
And the problem is
let's suppose at inference time, you cut
your text into words. And let's suppose
you have not seen a word at training
time,
you will need to mark it as unknown.
And so this thing is called OOV, out of
vocabulary.
So luckily, the subword level tokenizer
mitigates that problem.
Uh so you have uh
like um
a lower risk of uh OOV, but still you
you can have.
And as we mentioned, in terms of the
pro, uh you leverage the roots of the
words.
Um and then uh character level, uh you
know, it's robust to our misspellings
and our casing errors,
Uh but the problem is it makes
computations just like much slower and
your sequences would be like
very very long,
which will also make your I guess
inference time much higher.
Does that make sense? I guess this is
really the foundation of
I guess how to handle things with text,
but yeah, does that make sense overall?
Cool.
Okay, so now Okay, what we did is we
took
an input text.
What we did is we cut it into parts that
are basically tokens.
So in order for our model to understand
these tokens, we need to find a
representation for each of them.
So here we're going to take a look at
this, so that's called word
representation or more
I guess in a more correct way it should
be token representation. So we want to
find
a way to represent each of these tokens.
So the simple and naive way to do this
would be to just assign a one-hot vector
for each
word or for each token. So for instance,
let's suppose if Let's suppose we have a
vocabulary of three tokens,
book, soft, and teddy bears.
We would have let's say soft that is a
one zero zero vector,
teddy bear that is let's say a zero one
zero vector,
and book that is let's say a zero zero
one vector.
So this is called a one-hot encoding,
OHE.
We typically see
So cool. Yeah, this is a a way to
represent of our tokens, but
um basically what people want to do is
compare these tokens to basically see
which ones are more similar to what
other ones.
So common similarity measure that people
use is something called cosine
similarity. I'm not sure if you have
heard of it.
Um so you can think of it as just seeing
what angle these vectors make in the
n-dimensional space.
And
if I guess they are pointing the right
way in the same direction, then maybe
they're similar. Maybe if they're
orthogonal, maybe they're
kind of independent. And if they're
completely opposite, then maybe they're
opposite. That's
basically the mental model we want to
go into.
So the problem is
if you represent your tokens in a
one-hot fashion,
you will end up with all your vectors
being orthogonal to one another.
So that's a problem.
So ideally what we want is for tokens
that mean the same or similar to
basically have a high similarity.
And for tokens that are not similar like
on like about different things to be
more like orthogonal.
So here I just for illustrative
purposes,
teddy bears are are soft. So you want
teddy bear and soft to be I guess with a
high similarity. And let's say teddy
bear and book, which is kind of
independent, you want them to be closer
to zero.
So that's what you want.
That's what you have with one-hot
encoding and that's what you want.
Yep.
Uh sorry.
Oh, I see.
Uh the question is why do you care about
the norm?
Um
so
I guess cosine similarity is actually
normalized by the norms. So it's um
dot product. Oh, you mean why did I just
put dot product here instead of the
Oh, I see. And your question is why do
we not care about the norm?
Um
cool. I guess the viewers know the
question. Um I guess these measures,
they're all, you know, measures. They're
all ways to try to capture these kind of
similarity things.
Um
So I guess why do you not care about the
norm?
Hm.
I guess it's how people have tried to
kind of quantify that.
Um I guess you would need to see how
your vectors are trained and whether the
norm would be indicative of something.
Um
I guess the best answer I can give you
is I guess this is a measure. This is
not the perfect measure.
Um yeah, people may use also dot product
as a as a measure, but yeah, I don't
have like a great answer for you.
But as long as you capture I guess how
these vectors they're
they're pointing, I guess typically what
you care about is the angle between
them.
Um but yeah, typically you don't really
take into consideration the the norm.
Cool. Any questions? Any other
questions?
Yep.
It's a great question. So question is
around size of vocabulary and how that
would inform the choice with respect to
word, subword, and how that changes
across languages. It's a great question.
Um so I would say it really depends
first of all on the task that you're
trying to achieve. If your task is just
about one language, you would just
take that same language. You would
typically go with a subword tokenizer
just because of the reasons that we
mentioned here.
Um so I guess subword is a nice
trade-off between being able to identify
words by their roots, like leveraging
that, but also running less into the OOV
risk.
Um
So in terms of the size,
I know that people they've
you know
like tried different things. I think
typically for English you would target
something on the order of tens of
thousands of vocabulary size.
Uh but you know, like nowadays the
models
they're multilingual, they're also about
codes. So you will see that the
vocabulary size now is sometimes on the
order of of hundreds of thousands.
Uh okay, so with respect to Chinese, so
I guess you have this you know
difference in characters that you're
using. So for Latin,
I guess that's the alphabet we're all
accustomed to, but of course for the
other ones,
uh you have something similar, but in uh
I guess the the target language
character.
Um
So yeah, I would say order of magnitude
tens of thousands for one language,
hundreds of thousands if it's like
multilingual.
Um
yeah, these are the order of magnitude
that you want to target for us.
Cool.
Yep.
Great question. So question is how do
you get those embeddings? So it's
actually the next slide.
So we're going to talk about this.
Cool.
Great. So Okay. So now that we know
that the one-hot encoding is not a a
good way to represent tokens, what we
want to do is to learn
those embeddings from the data.
So I mentioned that there was this um
you know
paper that came out in the 2010s, so I
think it was 2013, that was called
word2vec.
And the reason why it was so popular is
because they showed a very intuitive and
interpretable
way of seeing these embeddings
because they were saying saying
something like, "Okay, king is to queen
what this is to that, like Paris is to
France what Berlin is to Germany." So
there was basically a way to make sense
of the embeddings.
So now the question is how did they do
that?
So they had two
ways of computing these embeddings. So
one way was called continuous bag of
words, the other one was called
skip-gram.
But they all rely on the same idea,
which is
let's just leverage
text that we have
and then try to predict
something that is part of the text based
on let's say the context.
So for instance, continuous bag of
words,
the goal is
you take into consideration the words
that are around a given target words,
and your goal is to predict that target
word.
And skip-gram is kind of the opposite.
You go from
a target word and you want to predict
the words that are around it.
So I guess this task is commonly called
a proxy task
because at the end of the day
in this exercise, what we care about is
not necessarily to
predict the next word, or at least not
yet.
Our goal is to learn
a representation of these words that are
meaningful.
And so here, the idea is
if you have a model
that somehow knows
how to predict, let's say, the next
word,
then it means that your model has some
understanding of how language works.
Which is basically what you want. You
basically want an embedding that is
reflective of
uh I guess what language is.
Which is uh you know, king and queen are
you know, are similar, you know, Paris
and France like this is the capital.
Like you you want to have these
associations
embedded in the representation.
And
let's go through a very simple example
of what that looks like.
So here in our example,
let's suppose that our proxy task is
about predicting the next word.
So here, what we take
is a very vanilla neural network model,
which basically
receives a vector of size V,
has some multiplication and a bias term
to get
uh like uh hidden states,
and then
uh another set of uh multiplications to
get our uh final vector.
So here it's basically uh
very simple neural network.
Uh so the input is of size V,
the hidden layer is of size D,
which is typically much smaller than the
vocabulary. So vocabulary is typically
like tens of thousands or hundreds of
thousands, so D is typically hundreds.
Like 768 for instance is is one example
uh of dimension.
So it's much much smaller.
So what we're trying to do
is to learn
the word representation through this
proxy task, and what we're going to do
is
try
to consider
the words
as inputs,
and predict the next word.
So let's go with the first word of the
sequence. So by the way, I use token and
words interchangeably.
Um so let's suppose we have the word A,
and we want to predict the next word,
which is the word cute.
So what we do
is we take the word A,
we take the one-hot
encoding representation,
and we pass it through the network.
So here, if you're familiar with neural
networks, so here you have uh I guess a
multiplication between I guess a matrix
and and this vector. So you have uh
hidden state representation, which is a
vector of size
D.
So here, let's suppose it's 0.2 and 0.9,
so D equal to
And then you have uh I guess another
pass here,
uh and then you get after softmax a set
of probabilities,
which are around
seeing what is the next word.
So in this example, we have
uh a vocabulary of size
six.
So the first word is predicted with
probability 0.2,
second word 0.4,
and then the other words are all 0.1 in
this example.
So let's suppose that we want
to somehow
be able to maximize our prediction to be
the second word of the vocabulary, which
is the 0.4.
So we basically compare
the prediction
with uh I guess 01000,
which is the representation of the
second word of the vocabulary.
And then we, you know, do the backprop,
we, you know, update the weights.
Not sure if everyone is familiar with
that part,
uh but the idea here is
once you obtain a prediction, you
compute the loss. So typically cross
entropy,
which will determine how far off
you are from the true answer,
and based on that difference, you're
going to update the weights
in order to make your prediction closer
to the truth.
So that's what you do, and then you
repeat that process. Let's suppose you
take the word cute,
which as we said is the second word of
the vocabulary, so the one-hot
encoding representation is 01000.
So you go through that uh you know,
network, uh you have uh hidden states,
like the vector is 0.8 and 0.4, you do
that again, and what you want to do is
to predict the next token, and here's
teddy bear.
And so you see now your model in this
example is predicting the next word to
be kind of like uniform, but you want to
somehow maximize the probability for
teddy bear.
So you go about doing this again and
again for all the words,
and at the end of the day,
you obtain a model
that
learns how to predict the next words,
which is basically the proxy task,
and what you're going to do
is to take the representation that the
model learns, which is the
the green units.
So what happens now is every time you
have a word,
you just represent that in a as a
one-hot
encoding representation, and you just
like multiply this
with these weights, and then you obtain
the green representation,
and that's
is your word representation.
Does that make sense? Yeah.
Yep.
Yeah, great question.
Yes, great question. So the question is
about what does V correspond to, and why
there's only six. So yes, in this
example, we only have six possible
words,
which is basically the vocabulary size.
Which is like very
um kind of a toy example, because in in
practice there's uh many more.
Um so I guess uh that's one of the
challenges with language. So you can
technically have many variation of
words, which is why if you take a word
level way to divide your text into
tokens, you can end up with the
vocabulary that's like very big, because
you need to account for all the
variations of given words.
Uh and the other thing that I want to
point out is um
let's suppose you have a vocabulary size
of six, and it's the six words that you
saw at training time. But what what
happens is if at inference time you have
a word that you have not seen
at training time.
And so the answer for that is typically
what people do is
they
reserve a spot
for what they call uh an unknown token
or out-of-vocabulary token.
Which is basically um
can think of it as, you know, a bucket
for everything that we could not have we
we were not able to identify.
So if let's suppose that inference time
you have a token that you were not able
to identify, they will all take that
representation, which is the unknown
token representation.
Um
and it's by the way something that
I guess the
word level tokenizer has kind of trouble
to do, because you will have a much
bigger chance of having
out-of-vocabulary tokens.
Word level subword level will have a
lower chance. And then character level
uh I guess you yeah, you don't have that
problem.
Does that answer your your question?
Yeah.
Cool.
Any yeah.
Great great question. So first question
is, when do you know when you're done?
So the thing with the proxy task is when
you train your model,
I guess your true objective is to not
really learn in this case to learn how
to predict the next word. Your objective
is to have meaningful representations.
But what you can do is to somehow track
the loss function for the proxy task
that you're pursuing,
but then also taking into consideration
that this is not necessarily your end
goal.
So I guess so one
uh you know, very reasonable way of
going about doing this is just to wait
until your model converges. So here what
you do is you track the loss as a
function of So there's this term epoch
which is how many times your model sees
the training set and so you compare
these these different curves and when
this converges it's typically like a
good time to you know stop stop the
training process and like just see if
that makes sense. Depends on your
downstream task of course.
But that's one.
Um
okay so your second question sorry can
you repeat the second question?
Yeah.
Oh great question. So
so the question is how do you know when
the generation stops? I guess like
otherwise it will stop it will never
stop. So yeah exactly so you have some
special tokens. Typically you have end
of sequence
end of sequence so typically when you
have the end of sequence token generated
then it's when when it stops.
All right so second question was
um
what informs the size of the hidden
layer? Um I would say it's a trade-off
uh because you want the embedding to be
rich enough that it can be informative
for your downstream task. So for
instance if you want to somehow get an
embedding of let's say your sentence
um and if you want to let's say do a
very very specialized task super um
you know like with a lot of different
outcomes maybe you want a vector that
recaptures that so maybe you want a
bigger vector but if you have like a
very simple task maybe a smaller vector
make make sense.
Um so I guess the size of your hidden
dimension
also impacts the complexity of whatever
you're running after because of course
if you have longer vectors you'll have
more computation so your inference will
be probably more expensive etc. So I
guess if there's a lot of factors so I
guess just to recap one is how
complicated your downstream downstream
task is second one is
how sensitive are you with like latency
cost all these things so it's really a
trade-off.
But out there you would typically see
embeddings of you know uh ooh of
hundreds or thousands.
Um
of course you know these models they've
been growing so number may change but
that's the the order of magnitude that
you're looking at.
Right.
This is indeed empirical yeah yeah. I
guess you can also rely on like
what others found uh and just go from
that. Yeah but 768 and yeah like these
numbers are are things that people
typically take.
Cool.
Yeah.
Good question. So um the question is how
can you distinguish words that are
spelled the same but in different
context? So you're way ahead of me.
Uh so this is basically the basics and
we're going to tackle
uh methods that can tackle these
problems of just contextualizing the
word in the sentence. Uh so yeah so
we'll see that in in a bit.
Cool.
I am not uh
uh I'm not on time so I'll I'll try to
get moving. Um so okay so now what we
did was see how we could learn
representations of tokens
but
I guess you may also want to get
representations of you know sentences or
you know pieces of text.
So one very
naive way to do that with what we saw
before
is to take something like the average
of words let's say the word
representations.
But the problem is you you know lose a
lot of meaning you lose the order you
lose um
and I guess here I think you pointed out
very well
uh the representations that you learn
are token specific regardless of where
they're at.
So that's why we have a class of models
that aim at capturing the sequential
nature of you know how text appears. So
we're going to talk about RNNs
which stands for recurrent neural
network.
So what RNNs do
is instead of processing words one at a
time
what they do is they keep a hidden
representation
of the sentence so far
and they consider tokens one at a time.
Uh so as I mentioned before this
technique was actually you uh introduced
uh like a fair amount of time ago so in
the '80s
um and
what this model does is it takes into
consideration
the order at which words appeared or
tokens appeared.
And so in this example um
you start
the I guess processing at the very
beginning of the sentence you have some
dummy um hidden state that is called A
typically noted A or H it's called a
hidden state activation or even
sometimes a context vector.
And you have some kind of a module that
takes into account
the hidden state so far
and the word at time step T. So here
time step one.
So here what it does is it takes in
the meaning of the sentence so far and
takes into consideration the words that
is happening now
and it produces an output vector
that's here can be used to you know try
to predict the next word so for instance
here we have the hidden state and this
um
representation of the words that then
you know you have some matrix
multiplications in this in this blue box
and you have an output vector that you
try to you know train on predicting the
next words.
And then
you keep on doing that
by
by keeping
these hidden states keeping track of
these hidden states.
And so you repeat the process and I
guess the way you would interpret these
hidden states is
it's a representation of the sequence
processed so far.
So the good thing with RNNs is now the
word order matters.
And you're also able to encode the
sentence in a more natural way.
So let's see roughly how it works. So we
have the same uh
favorite example so a cute teddy bear is
reading. So you would have the token A
you find the one hot encoding vector you
pass it through your network you compute
the hidden state you try to predict cute
but then you keep track of the hidden
states.
And then you input that into another uh
module and then uh you also consider the
next words. So you consider not only the
word itself but also the hidden state of
uh I guess the sentence so far and you
try to predict the next word again.
And again and again.
So this is RNN.
So
RNNs were used for a bunch of tasks and
just like mapping that straight to the
categories that we saw before.
For classification purposes
you can basically use the hidden states
of
the last
word in your sentence. For instance if
you want to predict you know the review
like the sentiment of a review you would
take basically the the last last vector
here and try to project it into the
space of uh the predictions or the
labels that you want to predict on. So
for instance if you want positive or
negative you basically project that
vector onto that space.
You can do that here for multi
classification so you would basically
have the representation of the token of
interest and you would project that
or for generation
you would basically process the whole
source text
and then have
uh kind of a the context vector aka
activation vector aka hidden states at
the end of your processing
which will then be used to decode
the output prediction.
So this is how you would use an RNN uh
for like each of these tasks.
So the reason why
you have not really heard of RNNs like
this like these days is because they had
uh you know some pros but a lot of cons.
So one of the cons is that the meaning
of of sentence
is basically solely encapsulated into
the hidden state.
So, you have this problem of long long
range dependencies, which basically um
like impacts your ability to
remember
what's the model saw in the past.
Which is why you have another class of
models that try to build on RNNs. So,
this class is called LSTMs, long
short-term
memory.
And the goal of that extension
is to have a way to somehow keep track
of the things that are  important
to remember
on top of the hidden state that we
talked about. So, here you have uh A of
T, which is uh you know, your
activation. Um
like basically the the sequence so far
encoded in there, and then you have
another
quantity that you track that is called
the cell state.
Let's go and note that C here.
So, this architecture aims at
I guess improving that piece, but I
guess it was not perfect either.
But yeah, so that was uh
like the main
um
issue of RNN-based methods, which is
that they have this issue of kind of
forgetting what was in the past. So, you
will see in the literature that this
phenomena is called
vanishing gradient.
And the reason why it's called that way,
so I know we're kind of running out of
time, but I'm going to just explain that
part.
So, in order for you
to predict, let's say, the last word,
you're basically dependent on
every hidden state that came before
that.
So far so good?
And so,
whenever you want to update the weights
of your model to match
the prediction here with the actual
prediction,
when you do the back propagation,
you somehow need to take into account
that
the last the value here is basically not
only a matter of this computation, but
also this computation or this
computation that basically happened in a
sequential manner.
So, you have this kind of uh
um
this phenomenon of trying to I guess
back propagate through time.
But the problem is
in practice, when you kind of write that
down, so it's a very ugly formula, but
when you write that down,
it ends up being
a product of of a bunch of quantities
that can So, if it's greater than one,
then it's exploding. If it's less than
one, it's vanishing. Cuz if you multiply
a lot of things that are less than one,
it just goes to zero.
So, I guess if you have something that
you're trying to update
that goes to zero, you basically have
trouble just like, you know, doing your
updates. So, that's the high-level
intuition.
This is not the focus of this class,
which is why I'm not going to the detail
of these ugly formulas, but
I hope you get the idea that uh for kind
of remembering things from the past,
it's not doing a great job because of
this uh sequential
um
I guess
uh characteristic.
Does that make sense?
Okay, I hope the next thing will make a
bit more sense, but before that, I'll
just recap what we saw. So, our goal is
to represent text.
So, we first started with represented
representing words or tokens, which was
what we tried to do with word2vec.
And we saw that, you know, it was a good
way to leverage you know, proxy tasks to
learn this representation, but we had a
bunch of uh limitations, and one of them
that you mentioned was that it was not
aware of the context. Uh and also the
word order didn't count.
Um and so, you have this uh other class
of methods that's is able to
take into consideration uh the words,
but then uh they have some trouble
keeping track of things when the
sequence gets very long, and you have
this problem of vanishing gradients or
long range dependencies. So, whenever
you see this term, it's basically
referring to that.
And also another thing that I have I
have not mentioned, but
the computations are very slow.
So, when you want to train these models
at training time,
in order to predict this word,
you basically need to
compute all the hidden states before.
So, where your when your sequence gets
very long, it just gets uh
like it just takes a lot a lot very long
time.
So, for all these reasons, for for I
guess all these what reason? So, for
the fact that um
the model has trouble remembering things
from the past,
people have tried having more direct
connections
between something and the thing from the
past.
And this is the idea behind
attention.
So, what attention does is it tries to
have a direct link
between what we're trying to predict
and something from the past.
So, in this example, let's suppose I'm
trying to translate an English sentence
into a French one.
So, here I guess the input sentence is
given. I'm, you know, computing the
hidden states, you know, I'm processing
words one at a time. This is my
traditional RNN. So, a cute teddy bear
is reading. So, here I have a hidden
state that I'm then decoding.
And you can imagine that
when wanting to
generate the next word of my
translation,
it would be great
if I knew
what word I'm trying to predict.
Or in other words, it would be great if
I could take a peek
at a certain area of the input text.
So, the idea behind attention is to have
a direct link
between what you're trying to predict
and things before.
This is the idea behind attention.
Um and so, it was introduced in 2014,
and uh yeah, again, this is trying to
kind of solve
for this long range
uh dependencies issues.
And so, yeah, this example wanted to do
that.
And
this concept is going to actually be key
for this class.
Cuz we're going to see that
the attention mechanism is
the thing that is going to make
everything, I mean, most of the things
work.
And this is actually the main principle
that the Transformer paper relies on.
So, the Transformer, which is the core
architecture that we will see in this
class,
has been introduced like or was
introduced in 2017 in this paper named
Attention Is All You Need.
So, even from the title, you can see
that, you know, the authors wanted to
just rely on that on that part.
So,
what the authors tried to do was to move
away
from these sequential way of processing
the text,
and instead let the model just have
direct connections with all
parts of the text at once.
So, that's is called self-attention.
Uh so, they tried that on translation
tasks,
and they just realized that, you know,
it was uh giving great results.
So, back to the example that we're still
using,
a cute teddy bear is reading.
Here, what we would say is that in order
to compute
the representation of the token teddy
bear,
we're going to look at all the other
tokens in the sequence
at once.
And directly with direct links.
So, I guess back to your question, here
we would have a representation of teddy
bear that would be unique
to the context that it is part of.
So, back to your question about river
bank and uh
uh robbing a bank, like here the bank
would have
uh different representations.
So, this is the idea.
I guess does the idea roughly make
sense?
And again, this is called the
self-attention mechanism.
Which and how am I doing on time?
Eight.
Eight? Okay.
Cool. Um so, okay, so this is the idea.
Uh so, now I'm going to just introduce
another
set of ideas, which is more terminology,
but it's going to be very important.
So, when you want to express something
in terms of something else,
we use the words key the sorry,
query, key, and value, Q, K, and V.
So, in this example,
our goal
is to figure out
what other tokens is the query teddy
bear more similar to.
So, here the question is, okay, you have
a query
and you want to see
what other tokens are most similar.
And so, what you're going to do is
to look at all the other tokens,
which are basically composed of
keys and values. So, you're going to
compare the query to the key
to quantify how similar your query is to
the given key
and take the corresponding value.
So, we'll see that in this example. So,
let's suppose you want to express teddy
bear as in terms of everything else,
what you're going to do is you're going
to take the query teddy bear
and you're going to
compare that query with all the other
keys
to see which elements is most similar
and then weight the more similar ones
and take their associated value.
So, that's a very high-level
uh idea of yes, how these things are. Of
course, we're going to see exactly how
they work, but that's the general idea.
Okay, cool. And speaking of query, key,
and value, we will also see
that one benefit of expressing things
this way
is that we can express
doing the self-attention computation
across the whole sequence in a matrix
format.
And GPUs love matrices, so it's really
like made for the hardware that we have.
Um and I guess what I mentioned here can
be expressed in the form of softmax of
the query and the key,
which is basically a way to get uh some
kinds of weights of which values will be
more important. So, for instance, if a
value is more important, you have a
bigger weight and another one will be
less important, you'll have a smaller
weight, and you basically
uh multiply that by the value.
So, don't worry, we'll have a detailed
example after. So, if it still
feels very, you know, high-level, fuzzy,
don't worry, we'll have a
uh details uh walk-through.
And yes, so this is uh how it works.
Okay, cool.
Any questions on
how self- or what self-attention is?
Yeah.
Great great question. So, the question
is uh what is value, what is key, I
guess how do you get those What do they
mean?
Um so, first of all, I just want to say
that these quantities, they're learned.
So, you are not fixing them.
But from an interpretation standpoint,
you can interpret that the key is there
for you to figure out which one is most
similar to the query
and the value is the actual value
that is associated with that with that
elements. So, here
you will have something like
you want to express this
in terms of all the values. So, the
weights in your weighted average will be
basically the dot product between
basically between the query and the key
and the value will be the actual vector
that you will use.
But again, this these things are learned
and there's something I've not
mentioned, but uh you mentioned it
correctly. So, we're going to actually
do projections
to obtain these quantities and these
projections are actually learned by the
model.
That's good?
Okay, cool.
Uh so, with that, uh we have
uh 15 minutes, right? To uh talk about
the architecture.
Um
Okay, so
at a very high level,
in order to make this self-attention
mechanism happen, the authors proposed
an architecture that is composed of two
parts,
an encoder, which is on the left side,
and a decoder, which is on the right
side.
So, the application that they have is
translation.
So, what will go through the encoder is
the input text in your source language
and what is going to go through the
decoder is the target language that
you're predicting.
So, the high-level idea
is you're going to compute
meaningful embeddings from your input
text
by passing them through the encoder
and you want that self-attention
mechanism to apply.
Meaning, you want to compute
representations of each token as a
function of others.
And you do that by using a layer called
the attention layer. So, multi-head
attention layer, but multi-head is just
doing this computation
uh you know, in different ways to just
allow the model to learn different
representations or different
projections.
But the idea here is you're going to
input
your
input text
and all the tokens in your input text
are going to attend to one another.
So, for instance, a cute teddy bear is
reading, you are going to compute
the representation of all the
tokens in this text
basically as a function of others.
And you're going to do that with the
encoder. So, here with the multi-head
attention.
Uh and then uh you have a feed-forward
uh layer, which is just to kind of let
the model learn uh another kind of
projection.
And what what you're going to obtain at
the end of your encoding process is
rich representations of
the tokens from the input sentence.
So, far so good?
But now your goal is to actually
translate
the input sentence. So, what you're
going to do
is to start your translation
with let's suppose the beginning of
sentence token, it's your first token.
And what you're going to do is
use
all the representations from your input
sentence
in order to figure out what to predict
next.
So, this what I just said is the cross
cross-attention layer, which is the the
one that is the second to all.
This one?
Which basically,
you know, you see I'm not sure if you
see the arrows, but there are two arrows
coming from the encoder, one arrow
coming from the decoder.
Can anyone tell me what the arrow from
the decoder stand like represents? Is it
query, key, or value?
Yes, there is. 1 over 3.
33% chance.
Who wants to try?
Is it key?
Okay.
Hm?
Query? Okay. So, the way to think about
it is you're trying to ask yourself,
what are the words from the input that
matter?
Right?
So, basically, you want to know, given
your query,
what are the
elements from the input that matter? So,
here this arrow is indeed the query, cuz
this is the thing that you want
to figure out.
And the keys and values are actually
coming from the encoder, which are
basically coming from the input
sequence.
Um and then you have another attention
layer, which is this one, and that one
is trying to
figure out
what other tokens of the output sentence
that you're decoding is going to be
useful to predict the next token.
So, let's suppose you, you know, started
decoding and you say
uh a new sample English, which is in
French,
uh to predict the next word, you want to
basically figure out
what are the tokens translated so far
that are going to be useful
to predict the next word. So, this is
what this attention layer is about and
it's called masked
because it only looks
at the tokens that translated so far.
It does not look at
tokens that were not translated because
of course they were not translated, so
there's no no way like on the right side
of the
of the token that you're trying to
predict.
Cool. Um
So, at a very high level, you have this
attention layer, which is present in the
encoder, which is present in the
decoder,
but it has
several, I guess, use cases. So, the
attention layer here aims at computing
embeddings from the input sentence
as a function of themselves.
And then, the ones from the decoder, so
the first one, the masked self-attention
layer, aims
at expressing something as a function of
everything that has been decoded so far.
And the second one, the cross-attention
layer, tries to
express things as a function of what
what has been seen in the inputs.
So, here, given that
you are
having direct links to different tokens,
you don't have this sense of order.
Right? Because in the in the RNN, you
were basically expressing things, you
know, one at a time. So, you had some
sense of the word order, but here you
don't have it cuz it's like a direct
links.
Which is why you have position
encodings,
which are there to inform on the
position of the word in the sequence.
So, we're not going to dig into that
today, but I just want to call that out.
So, at a very high level, and we're
going to see this in the detail example,
uh what we do is, in order to translate
a sentence from source language to
target language, we're first going to
tokenize the text, so, you know,
dividing into arbitrary units. We're
going to learn an embedding for these
tokens.
So, this is what the input embedding is
about. Then, we're going to have to add
some encoding with respect to the
position. We're not going to talk about
it to today, but just good to note.
And then, we go through the decoder.
So, the encoder tries to figure out how
to express things as a function of other
things from the inputs. So, it does that
in the multi-head attention layer.
And then, it goes through a feed-forward
neural network, which is just a way to
just project uh the
uh
the vectors to just like uh have some
more degrees of freedom uh to learn
things.
And then, once you have these
representations from the inputs, you're
then going to start your translation.
So, you start with the BOS token. And
what you're trying to do is figure out
what the next word is.
So, you're going to see, okay, what are
the words that were translated so far
that are useful for translation? So,
this is what the masked multi-head
attention layer does.
And then, you have another attention
layer, which is about expressing things
as
um as a function of what was in the
inputs, which is the cross-attention
layer over there. And then, you have a
feed-forward neural network uh to again
give some more degrees of freedom.
And at end of the day, you have a vector
that you then go through softmax.
And it just is a way for you to guess
what is the next words.
So, you have a vector of size vocabulary
size.
And you're going to use these values to
determine what is your next word.
Easy, right?
Any questions on this?
Yep.
All right. That's a great question. The
question is, what does head mean?
So, I guess I went too fast. I kind of
ignored that part, but when you do
the attention self-attention
computation,
you basically make queries interact with
keys and then take the corresponding
value,
but nothing prevents you from doing that
several times.
So, the term head
is given to the projection matrices that
you use to obtain the query, key, and
value.
And when you have several heads, what
you're doing is you're allowing your
model to learn different projections.
So, it's basically an additional degree
of freedom for your model to learn
different associations between your
vectors.
So, it's a great question. Uh so,
typically, it will be noted
lowercase h, number of heads.
Uh and this is what this corresponds to.
Does that answer your question?
Cool.
Very cool.
Um
Okay, we have a lot to discuss, but
here I have a slide actually for this.
So, this is the multi-heads that you
were mentioning. So, we're basically
running the self-attention computation
several times in parallel, again with
different projection matrices that uh
the model learns.
So, in case you have a computer vision
background,
it is similar to
having multiple filters in your
convolution.
Uh so, it's very similar it's the same
idea, but um I guess
different here. Yep.
Great question. The question is, uh are
the projections different? So, we're not
typically not constraining things.
We're just letting the model learn. But
in practice, it just tends to learn
different ways of seeing something.
Um so, yeah. But typically, there is no
constraint. Of course, you have, you
know, papers that dig into, you know,
how how about if you change this, but
typically, you don't have any
constraint.
Cool.
Uh great. Okay, I will just mention one
trick another trick that uh Transformer
uh authors use. So, it's called label
smoothing.
Who has heard of label smoothing here?
Okay. So, uh when you think here is, in
NLP,
when you want to predict what comes
next, there is typically more than one
way.
Like, when you say, "What a great
day, what a great lecture, what a great
book, what a great" There's always
multiple uh choices. Like, there's more
than one way of filling that gap. So,
label smoothing is a technique that
tries to intuitively address that.
And what it does is, instead of saying,
"Predict this word 100% is this word.
There is no other words."
What it does is, it says, "Okay, predict
this word, but there's a chance it's not
this word."
And in practice, what it does is, it
takes the one-hot encoding, and instead
of saying it's a 1 0 0 0 that you need
to predict, it says it's uh actually 1
minus epsilon and then epsilon over V uh
um minus one, I guess, um is what you're
trying to predict.
So, in practice,
it's a a method
that tends to make your model be more
unsure. Like, it will be less sure about
this prediction because you always tell
it, "Okay, uh try to predict this, but
actually, it's possible it's not it's
not the correct value."
But in practice, the authors see that it
tends to improve
metrics like BLEU, which is a kind of
proxy metric for translation tasks.
So, yeah. I think this method is like
pretty general for NLP, so yeah, it's a
good good one to know.
And with that, I think there's about
20-ish minutes left. So, yeah, Shervin
is going to
uh walk you through an end-to-end
example.
And with that, you
Yep.
The lou- Oh, you?
So, I guess here, you can think of this
as
um
something, I guess, some quantity. It's
not defined. So, some quantity.
Uh and yeah, the delta is like the like
one-hot, if you want. Yeah.
Something like this. Yeah. It can also
be a constant. Yeah.
Yeah.
Uh so, question is, uh is there a
relation with explore and exploit? It's
an interesting one.
Um
Mm. So, why would softmax give it for
free, by the way?
Right. But I guess it would still
So, I guess
at the end of the day, what you're
trying to do is to compare your
prediction with respect to the label.
So, I guess the question here is, do you
want to compare with 1 0 0 0, or do you
want to compare with
something that is not 1 0 0 0? So, I
guess the softmax does not allow you to
do that.
Exactly. Yes. So, I'm not sure if this
was super clear, but this is actually
the label. So,
what we're trying to predict is not 100,
but we change the label in a way that
makes the model
uh
I guess predict something that's less
sure, I guess.
Cool. Thanks.
And with that, yeah. Sorry.
Okay, great. Thank you, Ashish. And yes,
so we saw basically how the transformer
works. And now we're going to piece it
all together with the one specific
example.
Um okay, great.
So, let's take our favorite example
again. So, a cute teddy bear is reading,
and then we go
like all together through each step.
Um so, first we we start with
tokenization.
Um so, as we said, we we can use any
arbitrary decomposition to decompose
this into tokens.
Um and then, as someone mentioned, you
know, you need to have some way to
indicate uh like the start and the end
of a sequence. So, typically this is
done with the BOS and EOS tokens. So,
you add them.
Okay, so now let's focus on the
composition of each token
representation.
So, you have its embedding that is
learned.
And then, as Ashish mentioned,
in order to have an idea of what is the
position of the words or the token, I
should say, as part of the sequence, you
have some added information that is in
the form of a position embedding.
And here, the original paper
uses the convention of some sines and
cosines that it adds additively to the
representation. So, it's like a
element-wise addition.
Okay, great. So, now you have a
position-aware embedding for your token.
And you repeat that for each of your
tokens.
Okay. So, now you can see
all of these embeddings in the format of
a matrix, which is of size T model,
which is the size of your embeddings,
and then the other dimension is the
length of the sequence.
Um so, typically N.
So, all makes sense so far?
Any questions on the inputs?
Okay, great.
So, now we will send this representation
through the encoder.
Okay, so as Ashish said, you have this
concept of self-attention.
And the way you perform self-attention
is that you take this input and project
it on three spaces.
So, you project it
to the space WQ, you get queries.
You project the same embeddings in the
space WK, you get keys. And you do the
same for values, you get your values.
And then WQ, WK, and WV are learned by
the model. They're basically projection
matrices.
So far, so good?
Okay. So, now with all of that in hand,
you can apply the formula that Ashish
mentioned, that is the self-attention
formula, which is softmax of QK
transpose over square root of DK times
V,
uh which gives you another matrix out of
all of this.
Now, let's pause for a second and look
at how this computation is done in
practice and, you know, what every step
means.
So, let's look at Q. You know, when you
compute Q, you basically you project
your embeddings into that space. What do
you obtain? You obtain a matrix
where each row represents a given query.
When you say K transpose, it's basically
the same kind of matrix, but transposed,
where each column represents the key
representation of each token.
Now, let's mix them together with a
matrix
uh multiplication. So, when you multiply
each of them,
you see that each row represents the
projection of the query over each key,
such that
when you take the
like matrix multiplication and get the
softmax of all of this, you get a
probability distribution of the
projection of the query over keys
for each query.
Like each line will have this.
And yeah, I don't know if anyone asked
the question regarding, you know, why do
we scale by square root of DQ or DK? So,
it could be DQ as well, because
matrix multiplication
like the dot product here enforces the
fact that DQ equals DK.
And basically, what you see is that this
dot product,
as the dimension of key and queries
grows, it will tend to grow as well. So,
you want to normalize
this dot product, and this is why you
divide by square root of of the
dimension of of keys.
Okay, great. And then now you have your
softmax of all of these, and then you
multiply it with the matrix V.
And this is what Ashish explained as
having
the query
projected on the space of keys, and then
multiplied by the corresponding value.
So, the value is the representation of
the corresponding
key that we project on.
So, you end up with a weighted sum of
values for each query.
Okay, great.
Does that make sense so far?
Okay, awesome. And someone asked, you
know, what is the multi-head stuff? So,
you are right, it's not just single one
one time that it's done, it's actually
done each times.
And what you obtain is like all of that
is done in parallel.
And at the end, you obtain H
such matrices, and you concatenate them
with respect to the columns.
And at the end of this, you have another
projection matrix that you call WO,
that will project all of these back to
the original dimension of embeddings.
So, it's a way for the network to
basically have the dimension-invariant
way to bless you to go from
uh like the the original dimension back
to the original one.
Any questions?
Yep.
So, the question is regarding H. Is it
possible to get the same result each
time? And then if you concatenate the
same same thing, you know, will it be
helpful? Did I get the question right?
So, what makes it different? So, it's
the magic of gradient descent. So, the
network has an objective function at the
end. It has degrees of freedom. Its
incentive is to build a representation
that will be helpful to learn the next
word.
So, it doesn't have an incentive to copy
the same thing or do the same mechanism.
And this is why in practice you see the
model converge towards building
different representations that it can
then concatenate and then project into
something useful. So,
what what makes it such that you don't
have the same thing? Nothing. Like you
don't have any constraints, but the
nature of the learning that you let the
model
makes it do so in practice.
Any other questions?
Yeah, and then that that is a great
question. I mean, it's like typically,
yeah, gradient descent does wonders.
Okay, great.
So, now that we have gone through the
self-attention layer,
you have another component that is the
FFN. And I think there was a question
just here regarding how to choose the
dimension of the hidden layer with
respect to the input and outputs. So,
when Ashish mentioned word2vec,
typically you have a smaller dimension
than the input and and outputs. But
here, actually, the hidden layer is of a
bigger dimension than input and outputs.
And the rational for that is that you
want to have enough degrees of freedom
for the model to learn useful
representations.
So, it's a way to complexify the
features that you learn.
Um and yeah, just think to me.
Okay, great. And you don't have just one
encoder module, you have actually N of
them, BN in the original paper.
And at the end of all of this, you have
an encoder's
uh context-aware set of embeddings.
And then each of these set of encoded
embeddings will be those that will be
fed to the N decoders.
So, you have like a stacked
um stacked like succession of N
encoders, you have a stacked succession
of N decoders.
And the last representation of the
encoder is what we feed
to the cross-attention of each decoder.
Um
So, yeah, we're going to see that more
in detail.
So, how do we even start the decoding
process? So, you start with the BOS
token, basically saying to the model,
you know, "Hey, we need to predict the
next word. Uh you know, let's start."
So, what happens to the BOS token at the
very beginning?
So you feed it to the decoder and then
similarly as before for the encoder, you
have a self-attention layer.
And as I said mentioned, the
self-attention layer
is causal.
So the attention will be done on the
same token and the tokens that precede
it. So on on this first BOS token, you
don't see a difference because it will
just attend to itself.
But when you have
other tokens that you want to decode,
you will have this difference in where
you attend with respect to the decoder.
Okay, great. Goes through the
self-attention layer.
And then you have what I mentioned to be
the
cross-attention that takes as keys and
values
these encoded embeddings as inputs.
And then the queries are those of the
that come out of the self-attention
layer.
Okay, great. And then once you do this
cross-attention, you have just like in
the encoder, an FFN components that's
makes the representation richer. Was
there a question there? No.
Um
And then at the very end, so you do that
all of that end times and at the very
end of the decoding process, you have a
linear projection and a softmax layer to
turn um the prediction of the next word
into a probability distribution over the
vocabulary.
Okay, great. So we saw how to do that
for the next word here.
And
basically you do that again and again so
you have found your next token.
And then which is like one hot one hot
basically encoding of what you want and
then you take that embedding and then
put it back in the decoder and continue
this process.
And when do you stop?
It's a question for you all.
When you hit the EOS token, yeah.
Yeah, exactly.
Okay, great.
And with this process, it's basically
how the authors of this original
uh like landmark paper did machine
translation. So this is typically the
use case that was presented.
Uh yeah. Any questions?
Okay, awesome.
And with that,
thank you for your attention.
[Applause]